MATTHEW BREHMER, PHD

DATA VISUALIZATION RESEARCHER



- mattbrehmer@gmail.com
- **™** mabrehme@microsoft.com
- amattbrehmer.github.io
- ## aka.ms/mabrehme
- ☑ twitter/mattbrehmer
- in linkedin/matthewbrehmer
- Skype/matthewbrehmer
- github/mattbrehmer

I am a postdoctoral researcher at Microsoft Research in Redmond WA, USA, where I specialize in expressive information visualization design and data visualization for mobile devices. I am a member of the EPIC (Extended Perception, Interaction & Cognition) and Human Computer Interaction groups.

EXPERTISE

VISUALIZATION AND INTERFACE DESIGN

I design, develop, and deploy visualization tools and techniques for presenting and analyzing data, typically using technologies such as D3.js or R/Shiny.

EXAMPLES PROJECTS: Timeline Storyteller, Portfolio Sandbox, SoundConsensus, ShinyFork RELATED PUBLICATIONS: J6, J5, T3

QUANTITATIVE HUMAN FACTORS RESEARCH

I design and conduct experiments as a way to understand human capabilities with respect to perception, attention, and interaction; the findings of these experiments often lead to actionable implications for interface and visualization design.

RELATED PUBLICATIONS: J8, C6, C4, T2, C3, T1

QUALITATIVE HUMAN FACTORS RESEARCH

I evaluate existing data analysis and communication processes, work-in-progress designs, and deployed visualization tools by way of work domain analyses, interviews, chauffeured walkthroughs, and field studies.

RELATED PUBLICATIONS: J5, J2, W3, W2, TR1, T2

APPLICATION DOMAINS

DATA JOURNALISM AND STORYTELLING

Journalists, educators, and storytellers require expressive tools for presenting information to their audience. While at Microsoft, I have designed, developed, and promoted the use of such tools in the journalism community with the help of Microsoft's Data Journalism Program.

RELATED PUBLICATIONS: J4, J6

My PhD research included case studies of journalists who used the Associated Press' Overview Project to investigate large text document collections. Our findings provided transferable lessons for visualizing document collections and hierarchical data.

RELATED PUBLICATION: J2

ENERGY MANAGEMENT AND CONSERVATION

My PhD research included the design and development of visualization prototypes for analyzing and monitoring energy usage in portfolios of commercial buildings. I consulted with various stakeholders and prospective users, envisioning and implementing designs for interactively locating patterns and anomalies.

RELATED PUBLICATION: J5

M. BREHMER RÉSUMÉ | SEPT. 2018 P. 2 OF 8

APPLICATION DOMAINS (CONT.)

PERSONAL HEALTH AND FITNESS

My MSc research pertained to the design and evaluation of C-TOC, a computerized cognitive assessment tool intended for early detection of dementia. I studied the use of C-TOC prototypes by healthy older adults and by adults with diagnosed mild cognitive impairments. RELATED PUBLICATIONS: C4, J3, T2, W1

Prior to my MSc, I worked in the area of exercise video games: I studied the role of physical exertion on cognitive task performance. I also developed GAIM, an XNA/C# toolkit which allowed players with different input peripherals to play active games together.

RELATED PUBLICATIONS: C2, C1, T1

EDUCATION

DOCTOR OF PHILOSOPHY, COMPUTER SCIENCE

2011 - 2016

University of British Columbia (UBC), Vancouver, Canada

THESIS: Why Visualization? Task Abstraction for Analysis and Design

SUPERVISORY COMMITTEE: Tamara Munzner (UBC Computer Science), Joanna McGrenere (UBC Computer Science), and Ronald A. Rensink (UBC Psychology)

EXAMINATION COMMITTEE: Jason Dykes (giCentre, City University London), Alfred

Hermida (UBC Journalism), and Giuseppe Carenini (UBC Computer Science)

RELATED PUBLICATIONS: T3, J1, J2, J5, TR1, W2

MASTER OF SCIENCE, COMPUTER SCIENCE

2009 - 2011

Specialization in Human-Computer Interaction

University of British Columbia (UBC), Vancouver, Canada

THESIS: Usability and the Effects of Interruption in C-TOC: Self-Administered

Cognitive Testing on a Computer

SUPERVISED BY: Joanna McGrenere (UBC Computer Science) and Claudia Jacova (UBC

Medicine)

THESIS READER: Peter Graf (UBC Psychology)

RELATED PUBLICATIONS: C4, J3, W1, T2

BACHELOR OF COMPUTING

2004 - 2009

Specialization in Cognitive Science with Professional Internship

Queen's University, Kingston, Canada

THESIS: Assessing the Effect of Exercise Intensity on Cognitive Task Performance

in an Exercise Video Game

THESIS ADVISER: T.C. Nicholas Graham (Queen's School of Computing)

RELATED PUBLICATION: T1

EMPLOYMENT HISTORY

Postdoctoral Researcher

2016 - PRESENT

Microsoft Research Redmond, USA

Graduate Research Assistant

2009 - 2016

University of British Columbia Department of Computer Science Vancouver, Canada

M. BREHMER RÉSUMÉ | SEPT. 2018 P. 3 OF 8

EMPLOYMENT HISTORY (CONT.)

Graduate Research Intern Microsoft Research Redmond, USA	2015
Mitacs Graduate Research Intern Pulse Energy (now a division of EnerNOC) Vancouver, Canada	2013 - 2014
Graduate Teaching Assistant University of British Columbia Department of Computer Science Vancouver, Canada	2009 - 2011
Research Assitant Queen's University School of Computing Kingston, Canada	2009
User Interface Design Intern EMC Corporation (now Dell EMC) Toronto, Canada	2007 - 2008
Information Technology Staff and Web Developer Killam Properties, Inc. Halifax, Canada	2006
TALKS	
Slides from these talks are available at mattbrehmer.github.io/#talks. Talks with video recordings are indicated with the ■ icon.	
Tools for Expressive Information Visualization Design Microsoft Vancouver Data Visualization Symposium (Vancouver, Canada)	2018/08/01
Timeline Storyteller, from Visualization Design Space to Deployment The University of Calgary Data Empowerment Speaker Series (Calgary, Canada)	2018/06/18
Data-Driven Storytelling at Microsoft UBC School of Journalism Course on Special Topics in Contemporary Journalism: Data Viz (JRNL 520H) (Vancouver, Canada)	2017/10/24
Timelines Revisited: A Design Space and Considerations for Expressive Storytelling IEEE VIS 2017, TVCG Track (Phoenix, USA) RELATED PUBLICATION: J6	2017/10/03
Expressive Storytelling With Timelines Uber Visualization Night: A Journey Through Space and Time (Seattle, USA)	2017/08/31
Timelines Revisited: Considerations for Expressive Storytelling King's College London Department of Informatics (London, UK)	2017/07/11
Timelines Revisited: Considerations for Expressive Storytelling City University London giCentre (London, UK)	2017/07/10

TALKS (CONT.)

The Timeline Storyteller Custom Visual for Power BI Microsoft Data Insights Summit BI Power Hour (Seattle, USA) ▶	2017/06/13
Timelines Revisited: Considerations for Expressive Storytelling Northeastern University NUVis Visualization Consortium (Boston, USA)	2017/04/28
Timelines Revisited: Considerations for Expressive Storytelling Bentley University RealViz talk series (Waltham, USA) ■	2017/04/27
What Story Does Your Timeline Tell? OpenVisConf 2017 (Boston, USA) ■	2017/04/24
Timelines Revisited: Considerations for Expressive Storytelling Radcliffe Institute at Harvard University (Cambridge, USA)	2016/12/08
Why Visualization? Task Abstraction for Analysis and Design Dissertation Defence (Vancouver, Canada) RELATED PUBLICATION: T3	2016/03/23
Storytelling with Timeline Data Data-Driven Storytelling Dagstuhl Seminar (Wadern, Germany)	2016/02/11
Why Visualization? Task Abstraction for Analysis and Design Microsoft Research (Redmond, USA) ■	2016/02/01
Matches, Mismatches, and Methods: Multiple-View Workflows for Energy Portfolio Analysis IEEE VIS 2015, InfoVis Track (Chicago, USA) RELATED PUBLICATION: J5	2015/10/28
Matches, Mismatches, and Methods: Multiple-View Workflows for Energy Portfolio Analysis University of Washington (Seattle, USA)	2015/09/04
The Future of Data and Design In Visualization Research Vancouver Data Visualization Meetup (Vancouver, Canada)	2015/05/19
Overview: The Design, Adoption, and Analysis of a Visual Document Mining Tool For Investigative Journalists IEEE VIS 2014, InfoVis Track (Paris, France) RELATED PUBLICATION: J2	2014/11/14
Visualizing Dimensionally-Reduced Data: Interviews with Analysts and a Characterization of Task Sequences ACM BELIV 2014 (Paris, France) RELATED PUBLICATION: W3	2014/11/10
Pre-Design Empiricism for Information Visualization ACM BELIV 2014 (Paris, France) RELATED PUBLICATION: W2	2014/11/10
Visualization Task Abstraction from Multiple Perspectives IEEE VIS Doctoral Colloquium 2014 (Paris, France)	2014/11/08

M. BREHMER RÉSUMÉ | SEPT. 2018 P. 5 OF 8

TALKS (CONT.)

A Multi-Level Typology of Abstract Visualization Tasks

2013/10/15

IEEE VIS 2013, InfoVis Track (Atlanta, USA)

RELATED PUBLICATION: J1

Investigating Interruptions in the Context of Computerised Cognitive Testing for Older Adults

2012/05/10

ACM CHI 2012 (Austin, USA)

RELATED PUBLICATION: C4

A Tale of Two Studies: Investigating the Impact of Interruptions on Task Performance in Older Adults

2011/05/14

GRAND NCE AGM 2011 (Vancouver, Canada)

RELATED PUBLICATION: W1

PUBLICATIONS

Author copies of these publications are available at mattbrehmer.github.io/#pubs

PUBLICATION TYPES: J = journal article, C = conference proceedings, W = workshop paper, BC = book chapter, T = thesis, P = poster.

PUBLICATIONS AS PRIMARY AUTHOR

Visualizing Ranges over Time on Mobile Phones:

J8

A Task-Based Crowdsourced Evaluation

<u>Matthew Brehmer</u>, Bongshin Lee, Petra Isenberg, Eun Kyoung Choe To appear in Volume 25, Issue 1 (Jan. 2019) of *IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics* (To appear at IEEE VIS 2018, InfoVis Track).

Evaluating Data-Driven Stories & Storytelling Tools

BC1

A chapter in *Data-Driven Storytelling*, a book edited by Sheelagh Carpendale, Nicholas Diakopoulos, Christophe Hurter, and Nathalie Riche, CRC Press 2018.

Demonstrating the Value of Visualization:

P1

Highlights from the 2017 PacificVis Visual Data Storytelling Contest Matthew Brehmer, Kyungwon Lee, Ivan Viola, Jinwook Seo, and Bongshin Lee.

In Poster Proceedings of the 2017 IEEE VIS Conference.

Timelines Revisited:

J6

A Design Space and Considerations for Expressive Storytelling

Matthew Brehmer, Bongshin Lee, Benjamin Bach, Nathalie Riche, and Tamara Munzner

In Volume 23, Issue 9 (Sept. 2017) of *IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics* (Presented at IEEE VIS 2017, TVCG Track).

Why Visualization? Task Abstraction for Analysis and Design

Т3

Matthew Brehmer

University of British Columbia PhD Dissertation (April, 2016).

PUBLICATIONS AS PRIMARY AUTHOR (CONT.)

Matches, Mismatches, and Methods: Multiple-View Workflows for Energy Portfolio Analysis Matthew Brehmer, Jocelyn Ng, Kevin Tate, and Tamara Munzner In Volume 22, Issue 1 (Jan. 2016) of IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics (Presented at IEEE VIS 2015, InfoVis Track).	J5
Overview: The Design, Adoption, and Analysis of a Visual Document Mining Tool For Investigative Journalists Matthew Brehmer, Stephen Ingram, Jonathan Stray, and Tamara Munzner In Volume 20, Issue 12 (Dec. 2014) of IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics (Presented at IEEE VIS 2014, InfoVis Track).	J2
Visualizing Dimensionally-Reduced Data: Interviews with Analysts and a Characterization of Task Sequences Matthew Brehmer, Michael Sedlmair, Stephen Ingram, and Tamara Munzner In Proceedings of the 2014 ACM BELIV Workshop (Beyond Time and Errors: Novel Evaluation Methods for Visualization).	W3
Pre-Design Empiricism for Information Visualization: Scenarios, Methods, and Challenges Matthew Brehmer, Sheelagh Carpendale, Bongshin Lee, and Melanie Tory In Proceedings of the 2014 ACM BELIV Workshop (Beyond Time and Errors: Novel Evaluation Methods for Visualization).	W2
A Multi-Level Typology of Abstract Visualization Tasks Matthew Brehmer and Tamara Munzner In Volume 19, Issue 12 (Dec. 2013) of IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics (Presented at IEEE VIS 2013, InfoVis Track).	J1
Investigating Interruptions in the Context of Computerised Cognitive Testing for Older Adults Matthew Brehmer, Joanna McGrenere, Charlotte Tang, and Claudia Jacova In Proceedings of the 2012 ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI).	C4
Usability and the Effects of Interruption in C-TOC: Self-Administered Cognitive Testing on a Computer Matthew Brehmer University of British Columbia MSc Thesis (2011).	T2
A Tale of Two Studies: Investigating the Impact of Interruptions on Task Performance in Older Adults Matthew Brehmer, Charlotte Tang, Joanna McGrenere, and Claudia Jacova In the Work-In-Progress Proceedings of the the 2011 GRAND NCE AGM.	W1
Activate Your GAIM: A Toolkit for Input in Active Games Matthew Brehmer, Nicholas Graham, and Tadeusz Stach In Proceedings of the 2010 ACM Future Play Conference.	C2
Assessing the Effect of Exercise Intensity on Cognitive Task Performance in an Exercise Video Game Matthew Brehmer Queen's University B.Comp Thesis (2009).	T1

M. BREHMER RÉSUMÉ | SEPT. 2018 P. 7 OF 8

Charticulator: Interactive Construction of Bespoke Chart Layouts Donghao Ren, Bongshin Lee, and Matthew Brehmer To appear in Volume 25, Issue 1 (Jan. 2019) of IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics (To appear at IEEE VIS 2018, InfoVis Track). Property Best Paper Honorable Mention Award	J7
Reflecting on the Evaluation of Visualization Authoring Systems Donghao Ren, Bongshin Lee, Matthew Brehmer, and Nathalie Riche To appear the Workshop Proceedings of BELIV 2018: Evaluation and Beyond - Methodological Approaches for Visualization.	W5
What's the Difference?: Evaluating Variants of Multi-Series Bar Charts for Visual Comparison Tasks Arjun Srinivasan, Matthew Brehmer, Bongshin Lee, and Steven Drucker In Proceedings of the 2018 ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI).	C6
Data Visualization on Mobile Devices Bongshin Lee, <u>Matthew Brehmer</u> , Eun Kyoung Choe, Petra Isenberg, Ricardo Langer, and Raimund Dachselt In Extended Abstract Proceedings of the 2018 ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI).	W4
ChartAccent: Annotation for Data-Driven Storytelling Donghao Ren, Matthew Brehmer, Bongshin Lee, Tobias Höllerer, Eun Kyoung Choe In Proceedings of the 2017 IEEE PacificVis Symposium.	C5
TimeLineCurator: Interactive Authoring of Visual Timelines from Unstructured Text Johanna Fulda, Matthew Brehmer, and Tamara Munzner In Volume 22, Issue 1 (Jan. 2016) of IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics (Appeared at IEEE VIS 2015, VAST Track).	J4
C-TOC (Cognitive Testing on Computer): Investigating the Usability and Validity of a Novel Self-administered Cognitive Assessment Tool in Aging and Early Dementia Claudia Jacova, Joanna McGrenere, Hyunsoo S. Lee, William Wang, Sarah Le Huray, Emily F. Corenblith, Matthew Brehmer, Charlotte Tang, Sherri Hayden, B. Lynn Beattie, and Ging-Yuek R. Hsiung In Alzheimer Disease and Associated Disorders (July 2015).	13
Dimensionality Reduction in the Wild: Gaps and Guidance Michael Sedlmair, <u>Matthew Brehmer</u> , Stephen Ingram, and Tamara Munzner University of British Columbia Technical Report TR-2012-03 (2012).	TR1
The Haptic Crayola Effect: Exploring the Role of Naming in Learning Haptic Stimuli Inwook Hwang, Karon MacLean, <u>Matthew Brehmer</u> , Jeff Hendy, Andreas Sotirkopoulos, and Seungmoon Choi In <i>Proceedings of the 2011 IEEE World Haptics Conference</i> .	C3
Classifying Input for Active Games Tadeusz Stach, Nicholas Graham, <u>Matthew Brehmer</u> , Andreas Hollatz In <i>Proceedings of the 2009 ACM Advances in Computer Entertainment Technology (ACE) Conference</i> .	C1

M. BREHMER RÉSUMÉ | SEPT. 2018 P. 8 OF 8

ACADEMIC SERVICE

ORGANIZING COMMITTEE: IEEE VIS 2018 (Co-Chair: Visualization in Practice), the Data Visualization on Mobile Devices Workshop at CHI 2018, IEEE PacificVis 2017-2018 (Co-Chair, Visual Data Storytelling Contest)

PROGRAM COMMITTEE: IEEE InfoVis (2017, 2018), EuroVis State of the Art Reports (2017), IEEE PacificVis (2017, 2018), FAT*: Conference on Fairness, Accountability, and Transparency (2018), The Art of Networks III (2018), VIS Arts Program (2018), Information+ (2018), BELIV: Evaluation and Beyond - Methodological Approaches for Visualization (2018), Computation + Journalism (2019)

REVIEWER: IEEE InfoVis (2013 - 2016), IEEE VAST (2015), IEEE PacificVis (2017), IEEE TVCG (2015 - 2018), EuroVis (2014 - 2018), ACM CHI (2013 - 2018), ACM TOCHI (2013), Sage Information Visualization Journal (2015 - 2016), ACM SIGGRAPH Asia (2012), GRAND NCE ACM (2012)

STUDENT VOLUNTEER: ACM CHI Conference (2011, 2013, 2015, 2016)

UNIVERSITY SERVICE

UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON: Invited Project Judge for CSE 442 Data Visualization (2017)

UNIVERSITY OF BRITISH COLUMBIA DEPARTMENT OF COMPUTER SCIENCE: Graduate Admissions and Recruitment Committee (2013-2015), Guest Lecturer (CPSC 547: Information Visualization, 2014-2017), Curriculum Development (CPSC 444: Advanced Human Computer Interaction Methods, 2010-2011), Teaching Assistant (CPSC 444: Advanced Human Computer Interaction Methods, 2010; CPSC 344: Introduction to Human Computer Interaction Methods, 2009)

UNIVERSITY OF BRITISH COLUMBIA COMPUTER SCIENCE GRADUATE STUDENTS' ASSOCIATION: Vice President (Social Affairs) (2010-2011), Graduate Student Orientation Committee (2012), Organizer of the Un-Distinguished Lecture Series (2010–2011, 2012–2013)

QUEEN'S UNIVERSITY COMPUTING STUDENTS' ASSOCIATION: Student Orientation Leader (2005), First Year Representative (2004-2005)

AWARDS

IEEE VIS: Best InfoVis Paper Honorable Mention (2018) for J7 (Charticulator)

UNIVERSITY OF BRITISH COLUMBIA: Student Service Award (2016), Volunteering Award (2015), Mitacs-Accelerate Graduate Research Internship Program Award (2013-2014), Natural Sciences & Engineering Research Council of Canada (NSERC) Postgraduate Scholarship (2011-2014), Four Year Doctoral Fellowship (2011-2015), Department of Computer Science Merit Scholarship (2009-2011)

QUEEN'S UNIVERSITY: Dean's Entrance Scholarship in Computing (2004-2005)

REFERENCES

References are available upon request.